A Guide to the Governor L. Douglas Wilder Virginia Liaison Office, 1985-1994
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Governor L. Douglas Wilder Virginia Liaison Office, 1985-1994 (bulk 1990-1994)
The Library of Virginia
35539
1.4 cu. ft. and 4 boxes
Virginia Liaison Office
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from Governor L. Douglas Wilder.
Historical Information
The General Assembly established the Virginia Liaison Office in 1978 (Chapter 505, 1978 Acts) to be an institutional link between state and federal governments as well as Virginia and other states. The Virginia Liaison Office (VLO) represents the Governor before both Congress and the federal administration, advocating for the Commonwealth's interests in Washington, and monitoring federal developments that affect the state. The Office is responsible for monitoring and tracking federal legislation that is of interest to the Commonwealth and keeping the Governor's Office and state agencies up to date on the status of federal legislation and regulations. The Office is also tasked with influencing the development of federal legislation and regulations by keeping the Virginia Congressional Delegation informed about the Governor's priorities and maintaining contact with Congressional staffs, key federal agency official and public interest groups. Other duties include alerting state agencies and local government to federal grant opportunities and monitoring the progress of any grant applications, writing or advising on testimony to be presented by the Governor or state agency heads before Congressional committees, resolving administrative issues between state and federal agencies, and maintaining liaison with other states and interstate groups. The VLO is also required to report twice a year to the Senate Finance Committee, the House Appropriations Committee, and to the Governor's Office on all federal mandates and regulations which may have an effect on the Commonwealth. In addition to this, the VLO also works with interstate and regional organizations in which the Governor participates, such as the National Governors' Association, Southern Governors' Association, Appalachian Regional Commission, Southern States Energy Board, Southern Regional Education Board, and the National Capital Region. During the administration of Governor L. Douglas Wilder, Glenn K. Davidson (1990-1992) and Dian Copelin (1992-1994) served as the Director of the Virginia Liaison Office.
Scope and Content
Records, 1985-1994 (bulk 1990-1994) of the Virginia Liaison Office during the Wilder administration containing articles, correspondence, notes, reports, and other documents concerning U.S. military bases' potential closing and conversion; Virginia's congressional delegation; federal budget and state priorities therein; and federal legislation affecting health care, voting, taxation, transportation, and the environment. Records also relate to the state Attorney General's Office, state Policy Office, the National Governors Association, and the Southern Governors Association.
Contents List
- Virginia Liaison Office annual legislative report, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Attorney General's Office, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Policy Office, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Policy Office: subject files, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Policy Office: subject files, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- National Governors' Association, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- National Governors' Association, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- National Governors' Association, testimony of Raymond C. Scheppach, executive director, before the Joint Economic Committee Hearing on State Programs for Defense Adjustment, 19 May 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- National Governors' Association briefs, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Southern Governors' Association, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Congressional Delegation meeting, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Congressional Delegation meeting--briefing materials, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Congressional Delegation meeting, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Congress budget reduction package, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Congress's Spending Choices in 1992 Appropriations Bills--memorandum, 13 December 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Federal legislative status report, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Virginia's federal legislative and regulatory priorities, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Federal priorities--background research, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Federal budget--report on implications, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- House budget deliberations, fiscal year 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Department of Defense conversion--federal research materials, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Analysis of the Industrial Structure of Virginia's Defense Industry, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Listing of Virginia's Prime Defense Contractors Ranked by Contract Amount, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Defense conversion, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Defense conversion--budget funding, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Economic conversion and defense spending, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Defense conversion and economic adjustment--speeches and remarks, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Governor's Commission on Defense Conversion and Economic Adjustment--First Report to the Governor, November 1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Estimated Private Sector Defense Employment by Industry and Region in Virginia, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Defense conversion--California response, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Military--defense base closures, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Military--defense base closures--Cobra realignment summary, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Military base closures, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Military base closures--National Association of Counties--Impact of Base Closures and Realignments on Affected Communities, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Program Information Package for Defense Technology Conversion, Reinvestment, and Transition Assistance, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Vint Hills Farm Station, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 12)